hello and welcome back to voicecraft a
medium for artful and experimental
conversations
that seek to share insight into the
nature of psyche
culture and our relationship to an
evolving world at the turn of an age
it's part of a broader culture-making
vision to build wiser pathways to
connection and collaboration
and more effective protocols for
sense-making and generative
meaningful and healthy interaction there
are breadcrumbs to follow
if you look
i think what i i think part of what i
heard there was um
this relationship between the wisdom of
crowds and also the madness of crowds
and i think what's most important is the
capacity to discern in whatever the case
is in fact the wisdom um and
that there's something else that's
really coming
coming through to me here when we speak
about vision
and fabric and it's the notion of
religion it's a notion of something
we can all gather around in some sense
even if we want to
understand that center as a wandering
center as a moving center
to continually be re-realized and
re-woven
still some inner orientation towards
something that together we can
share in and that there's a
bi-directionality to that there's both
the classic conservatism and progressive
thing to put it in
sort of more topical language but a deep
care for
the lineage and the vitality of where
one's been where we've been together
and what we're caring about now and then
also what it is we have to
adapt to and the sort of the the valley
to cross and the land beyond so how do
we
reorient such a such a broad thing in
this time
i just wonder you know i have a lot to
say about this but
i'm wondering where the notion of
religion
and um plays into this this
feeling um this sense
of this
so so eric you know when you're
mentioning how you know the that the
rebel is just as trapped
it's like there's a sense in which
someone who's just taking the contrary
position isn't yet
able to really participate in the
generative thing together there's still
a kind of lock
there right they might not have a belief
maybe that
it is actually possible to to really
step into
a deep not knowingness but actually
somehow be caught in a kind of process
to be held in a kind of process or at
least go there together
i i you know i'm not saying it always
has to be like a nice soft
holy pleasurable thing at all but that
we can actually
go hang on a second like step the
back is hey
is like when when that point
comes when it's like no actually we've
forgotten some extremely important
things
you begin to put the put the like steps
forward a little bit to confront hey
and go how have we really so have we
really forgotten something
can we can we go somewhere together all
these kind of these energies that i've
just kind of
that i've infused in this little dynamic
here i'm interested in
what religion is like how you hold the
concept of religion and it's important
in this time yeah so
okay um what comes up for me when i hear
the word
religion is that at least how it
functions in my mind and how i see it
function in most
people's mind is that and young has a
great quote that i don't remember
exactly but
religion is the barrier that keeps
people from experiencing god
and the way that i understand that is
religion as
it's used is a set of principles
or behaviors that you ought to do
to be a part or to connect to whatever
this version of divinity is that's been
taught to you
um something about the death of god as
pronounced by nietzsche
ushered in this incredible and probably
terrible responsibility that it feels
like
and this is what my life has felt like
and i'm sure it's going to resonate for
both of you is that
we now live in a time where we have to
create our own religion
like personal religion within each of us
and really on some level i think that
that's your personal philosophy
and that the only way to create your
religion is you have to learn how to be
quote unquote spiritual but what i feel
that means is
can you learn how to feel into
what is trying to come out of you and
then you enact it
in the world as an experiment and then
anything that improves
the world around you hold that as a
principle for the time being
and then continue to act out the
principles that arise through you
be humble enough to put down the ones
that don't improve your life in the way
that you feel called to improve it
and then you slowly start to build up a
set of you know hypotheses for how to be
as a being in the world to make it a
better place
and then your being becomes the
testament of whatever your personal
religion is
and then the way admiration function
people is that it's not a conscious
choice you don't get to choose who you
admire it's something that comes through
you
and so then if people start to admire
the principles that you're enacting in
the world you can use that as more
feedback and that it
feels like religion is
the stultified version of spirituality
and that we live in a time where no
cement structure
is going to be the thing that gets us to
tomorrow
and that people have to learn how to
bring forward their
personal spirituality and then we have
to communicate
we have to share what we believe these
ideas are
we have to be willing to be seen you
have to be willing to be critiqued we
have to be willing to
transform and my intuition is that
there's a collectiveness that's
happening
through the um rise in connective
technology where there is
an unnamed yet religion arising
that will never be called a religion
because the moment you call it a
religion you put you try to put a box
around god
but it feels like there's a new
spirituality
that's arising that i hope continues to
argue with each other in a way where it
continues to
adapt and evolve and that i think that
religion in some sense is dead forever
through that interpretation of religion
i think religion's still got some juice
in it yet
but i also think that
when we talk about religion i mean we're
we're falling into a certain
kind of um particularly very western
language game
yeah and you know religion
the concept of religion as like a dewey
decimal category
um of things in the world
is i think very tied up with
um the concept of church orthodoxy
in this very specific way right and you
know church orthodoxy obviously didn't
stop
gnostics and cathars and greek orthodox
and russian orthodox and
right and any number of other split off
groups um
and then eventually protestantism which
really blew the cap off
but but the idea of
of a sort of like a large centralized
authority on
doctrine is of in some sense very
western right
when you know uh religious studies
scholars and anthropologists you know
went into other cultures you know we
went in
to india and we said you know hinduism
buddhism
but what we were really describing was
like a huge variety of
local practices and local deities and it
was diverse
as diverse in a sense as you know
languages right language diversity in
in an area and so you get these
expressions which obviously
share a certain amount of underlying you
know
shared material because the humans are
in proximity but the idea of trying to
be like
hinduism it's not it's just it's not a
thing
in the same way right it's there's a
diversity of expression
in the diversity um
and i think that in the same way as
latin right bound the west
and the church abound the west religion
is similarly
it's a kind of yoking right it where it
binds to cultural consciousness in a
certain way
now on one hand yeah i think that that
has probably had at least in its current
formulation
sort of its heyday um as this goes
forward people are going to be playing a
much more syncretic
and a much more a little of this on a
little of that like
you know going to a nice market kind of
approach
but um i guess i think about it
in two ways one those old rituals
you know the old rituals the old
liturgies the old formulations of
myth uh often have a surprising
amount of power left in them right um
provided you can connect
and you know it's a little bit like when
you're talking in magical terms you know
in
in the 70s there was a big rise in chaos
magic
and chaos magic had this very like
idiosyncratic do-it-yourself
individualize your myth kind of thing
hit in the 70s maybe peaked in the 90s
somewhat declined right
and it's a cool idea that you can you
know do a magical ritual
and summon you know james bond for
confidence and that fundamentally
what you're dealing with in any event is
sort of a narrative
entity right um however you want to put
the metaphysics on there
right um but there is something to be
said for the old
the old stuff like it's the the blood
runs deep you have to
really drill in a sense you have to like
concentrate to get in but when you
connect
you're connecting with something that
has the rhythm
and the routine of generations and
generations of humans
it has influenced the culture code in
all of these ways
right which is why as much as people
talk about i just don't think
christianity for instance is down for
the count
i think it's due for a massive
transformation that's probably
1500 years overdue or so
but um you know but like the
fundamentals there and some of the
fundamental
i mean you know i was raised like half
catholic
uh so my mom's a catholic heretic
and my dad is nominally anglican but
he's actually just a he's a kind of a
pothead science fiction fan so in
those two streams you know come together
and so you know i was the questioning
skeptical kid in my grade school
um like i got tossed at a religion class
on the regular
um but when i reconnected to that stuff
at about 20
and you know through i wrote a novel
about christ i started reading the
gospels in as close to the original
formulations as possible
i did a lot of you know general
scholarship about jesus and i listened
to jesus christ superstar
the uh the film version soundtrack
non-stop
for like i don't know months
um and the effect that that had right
really just like
soaked in like i got this this
tremendous respect for
um some of those myths and things that i
had taken for granted as being just like
down to the count
right i was like no it's not like
there's there is a vital current here
um but it needs something
and i guess the way that i think about
it is that
you know when we talk about sort of
spirituality or religion
when we talk about that binding function
of religion what we're talking about is
authority
right it's it's authority and both like
in the sense of like
you know epistemological authority but
also political authority and right
authority
and i think that the way forward and
obviously this ties into my own work
is that we need to invest that sense of
authority
um and and thus the kind of the unity
that can bind together our experiences
um in something else and i mean my pitch
is obviously
science that science needs to be playing
an integral role in this
and that to the extent that science
stops ignoring this
and it finally is to be fair and right
honestly you can go back pretty far
right scientists in previous
uh centuries had no problems thinking
about this stuff
and you know william james right is a
huge pioneer of religious
studies but also of psychology you know
at large
and i think returning to that jamesian
mold not necessarily perennialism
of trying to like just everything boils
down into the same thing
but instead looking at this stuff
scientifically and realizing that
our shared inheritance
as human beings massively outweighs the
differences which doesn't invalidate the
differences they're important
but it gives us a framework um and to
the extent that we study it we can
understand
like what is it that matters to us in
religion well what matters is
awe in the sense of the sacred the sense
of transcendence
and the production of meaning and the
ability of stories to
to reflect back and enrich and inform
and right these are things that we can
look at
out of any specific religious context
and thus
enable that kind of thing where we can
be doing personal exploration but
there's something that we can
we can refer back to there's some you
know pole star to guide by
it's the second time the pole star came
up anyway
and the thing that resonates the most
with me is that it really
feels like the call of this time is to
help science
learn how to bridge to the
meaning and the value truths inside of
religion
and instead of seeking to destroy
seeking to integrate religion without
the orthodoxy
without the political authority
and like you know because the
most the most convincing language of
modern people now is science or what
people think is science and there's all
sorts of ways that it can be manipulated
and such
or at least to the conscious mind and
that if science can find a bridge to
religion and to excavate the gold and
the living
essence that's still there i i feel is
one of the most important tasks
yeah science i think done right and
science is often done poorly
but of course science done right you
know anytime people get bent out of
shape it's like but they just found a
new thing that contradicted the old
thing
it's like good then they're doing their
job exactly that's what that's what
they're supposed to be doing it's
supposed to be churning folks
because you know the whole point is that
it's a constant
unfolding it's a constant we're not
going to get to the end
science contra what some people think
doesn't have
a terminus it's not i don't think anyway
i mean it could be wrong i suppose
but i think it's just like we're just
going to continue to move into the
twilight horizon
and the intuition is that whatever this
thing is is infinite
like whatever you want to call it is
it's infinite and so of course there is
no
end point in the understanding of
infinity right
and it's just gonna it's gonna
revolutionize as it goes right as our
sense of scale and our sense of whatever
in the depth of our dynamics and is
going to just keep
turning over and one thing to bring us
back around
you know science science in a sense
often runs opposite
conventional dogmatic narrative because
it does two things
it has built into it this process of
self-revolution
right very much so in a way that you
know
theology or something might resist
fairly strenuously
but the other of course is that it
deeply weirds things
so people often talk about science
disenchanting the world
and i i just think that couldn't be
further from the truth
um common sense takes the
um takes the um sort of unfamiliar
and explains it in terms of the familiar
but science takes the familiar and then
explains it in terms of the unfamiliar
yeah it makes everything much weirder
much weirder
um and so that right um now whether or
not culture at large can handle that
as a central ethos is not clear right
because that's
in some ways a minority position that's
hard for people to come to
um it it challenges their sense of
stability and
and all kinds of stuff and it pisses
them off um
but i think if we could get that going
and then maybe connect it up i think
with something else you said which is
the
the in some sense the the
democratization or at the very least the
egalitarian distribution
of inactive myth-making
right right so that we're not being
given
myths in the same way but we're
producing them and
that's of course one of the reasons i'm
so big on on role-playing again
is i sometimes see it as this kind of
historical emergence it was really
nothing like it
60 years ago and 50 years ago it comes
on the scene and it sort of emerges from
war gaming
innocuously but then since then the
basic concepts and stuff
have been making these steady secret
invasion kind of inroads into the
culture
that have massively altered the way that
we think about
games the way that we think about
stories right
mass media you know i don't think you
could have game of thrones in some sense
without
having that kind of gaming and you know
the direction people often go on it is
they're like well what role-playing
games do is of course they
sort of they pre-figure virtual reality
but and and maybe they do uh certainly
the language is going to end up borrowed
the same way as it was for for video
games right
uh millions billions of people play
pokemon and have no idea that
levels and hp and all that stuff is
that's just dnd code
but um but i think even more interesting
is like the way that
especially the current explosion what it
does is it passes
it passes these tools for like small
group
idiosyncratic myth-making and value
production
and dramatic storytelling in in what is
in many ways the oldest
art form right verbal storytelling a
certain amount of animated pictures
right
it it brings us back to the campfire
with
you know some rules and some dice
because we're grown up and we want to
you know deflect the arguments
right but but if we can sort of do
that and link it up with
psychotechnologies right if we can go
into
you know the the shattered cathedrals as
it were
and and take the stained glass windows
out of them and bring them into the
light
and and hook them up to something that's
that's that's self-regenerating and
and sort of weirding like science
that i think is the sort of engine that
might actually get us through
the narrow gate that faces us and i'm an
optimist too
to be fair uh i'm just an optimist that
sweats heavily every time i read the
news
i love the idea
and i got goosebumps when you
articulated that
there is something up there is something
almost implicitly
in in subversive about role playing in
the sense that it allows
people to learn how to generate their
own myths and
then to embody those own myths inside of
a game and game is one of the
oldest like structures that the
conscious mind
has created to help guide action and
i know for me personally like i was
raised
on role-playing games not television you
know like
i grew up in a family where everyone
else was watching tv
but i was playing final fantasy for 50
or 100 hours and
i was learning about mythological uh
creatures i was looking i was learning
about gods i was learning about
what it means to be heroic and like my
path compared to everyone that i grew up
with
is so fundamentally different and it
feels like a huge part of that is
because i played role playing games
um yeah and i mean the thing is it's
and this sometimes surprises me when i
consider but all that's in its infancy
yeah like especially tabletop video
games of course have inherited a lot of
it and they've become massively more
sophisticated
um but even tabletops only 50 years old
50 years there are a few things that are
like
you know um go back a little further if
you sort of dig around in the historical
record
but like it's a more recent technology
than radio
and so like you know
a significantly more recent technology
it's more recent than television
and yet it's a kind of it's a thing that
it's almost shocking it never existed i
mean you could have had it in the roman
empire they had all the bits
it's just that it didn't emerge and
i think there's something that that i
often
speculate is there which is that
when you have a culturally unified ethos
of storytelling be it religion
or general mythology and stuff there's
already that
structure and like it's it's interesting
mostly not that it was never used as
propaganda it was
but that that being within that
structure sort of met those needs and
people so people
if you were a bard or something maybe
you you would
ad lib and write and and embellish and
tell stories and add stuff and in the
oral traditions that's often the case
but for everybody else they were just on
the receiving end and i think
what we're really starting to see is
that that participatory aspect
which takes us back into ritual
participatory drama is ritual it's
putting on a role it's draping yourself
in the
you know the the animal skin hood yes
and then taking on the form of the
animal
and you know as somebody who runs games
right
somebody runs games one of the things
that i like to point out to people is
i play all the bad guys this is the
shadow workout
like you can't get in therapy man
because
because i can just be an absolute
bastard and that's what they want
that's what everybody wants you want a
good antagonist no good villain no good
story
in a basic story and so i get to be
absolutely like
like a grind and yet i can put it into
the space
where everybody gets a cathartic payoff
where i don't have to take my
monstrousness
uh and excessively embody it in the
world um
right but instead i get to like move
into these spaces that might otherwise
be
quite frankly kind of terrifying to to
inhabit in other contexts right
so yeah i don't know i sorry i could go
on about this stuff all day but
so that really
um resonated with me is that it's so
again it's this idea that like if psyche
is like the ocean you cannot
concretize over it it will always burst
births
through and that when organized religion
really lost
the function that it serves in the
psyche when it you know kind of
disintegrated in the last 100 years
it had to come out through some other
way and one of the ways that it's
erupted back through is through
role-playing
i recently read a book called we by
robert johnson are you familiar with
it i am yeah it's a whole he she we
yeah there's like a sequence of them
yeah right and
the idea of we is he articulated that
one of the other places where the
function
that religion sought to meet erupted
back through
when the container was kind of destroyed
is through romantic love
and that it's the projection of the
divine onto the partner that then allows
you to work through
you know all of the aspects that we
sought to have
met through religion and so these feel
like two
prime examples in our lifetime where
like young talked about you can destroy
the container but the archetype will
just go underground
you know and that these seem to be two
of the
big primary ways that um whatever it is
that the psyche
seems to need in order for it to be
healthy it's finding new containers and
two of them are the projection of the
you know inner
god onto the romantic partner and then
also role playing
and the other thing that you shared is
um the catharsis that can come through
role playing of working out your shadow
it's exactly the same type of
articulation
that i hear from people that consciously
explore
bdsm like what right
which is structured into scenes and also
has dungeon masters
exactly yes and that um what i find is
people
who have complex ptsd they actually seem
to be the ones who gravitate towards
bdsm
when it's done consciously and
intentionally it actually
allows them to like almost
replay the scenes that their inner child
would had to have played out in order to
you know not be traumatized
and it feels like uh i love that you
just connected scenes and dungeon
masters and it's the exact
like to me all of this
is more evidence that the psyche
is so powerful at seeking whatever it
can find in its environment to heal
and to grow in the same way that
wherever you plant that
seed it is going to use
every possible resource in its
environment to grow
yeah i mean one of the things about
working with the unconscious i think
that's
wonderful but also sometimes frustrating
right is that
it exceeds our conscious scope by such a
huge factor right that it's like when
you know people really want a sense of
finality it's right they want to be able
to go through a process and finish it
it's like no you don't understand
like you never you're never done you're
never done
because you can't be because it's
impossible because it's so much bigger
than you right
and by the same token um
i think you know the the
you know the fact is that it's it's thus
more adaptable than we are and more
mercurial than we are it can always find
another way in
it's smarter than we are in some sense
right
doesn't matter which what
constructions we end up putting up
it can figure out a way around and my
experience with complexes especially i
mean even if they're kind of screwing
with you
they're very clever about it right they
can they can do these really clever
you know workarounds romantic love is an
interesting one
i i have to admit that's actually
something that worries me a bit
when i consider it um i remember
johnson's point
in we and i sometimes worry that
you know after we sort of shoved god off
the throne
that looking for a sort of a pivot point
for the universe
we we enthroned romantic love right
right
and not the right move it's the problem
with it is that it
trying to make another human being the
pivot point of the universe is unfair to
them
and unfair to yourself and like you see
it with projections all the time right
where you know one member of the couple
is like oh my god they're perfect
they're perfect in every way
and the other member of the couple is
probably
saying something more like they're not
perfect but i'll change those things
uh and both of them are disappointed one
wears through the illusion and it's like
what you're human
this is not what i signed up for i
signed up for a divine being
and the other one is like i have failed
to transform you into my
particular divine being that i had in
mind and everybody walks away pissed off
that they didn't end up with a a perfect
lover of limitless erotic capacity an
absolute best friend
a you know business partner a like
a replacement for you know the all
meaning
um so i worry about that sometimes and a
lot of that is about the erosion of
friendship
um you know people localize themselves
in one relationship
because families are more atomized
friendship is
not you know like i was remarking to my
my partner actually the other day
i was like there are couples therapists
why are there no friends therapists
yeah yeah don't know because the answer
just said rocks me because i find that
my one of my complexes is i try to make
my romantic partner
also my best friend and that that
puts too much pressure on them and that
feels like that's something that like
we've evolved being a tribe
you know and to disperse that weight
amongst many
yeah yeah this is this has been a
really beautiful um train
progression dialogue here that i've
really enjoyed witnessing
an image did come to me though i feel
like i i feel like i'm watching a
beautiful ship
and i just took a jump in the ocean and
i'm trying to catch up back with the
ship now
um and i've got like hey guys i've got
like a couple planks here you know i
feel like i wanna
i wanna add them on to the ship um
because uh so so there's a couple
interesting themes coming through um so
you've mentioned the importance of
science
the importance of participatory myth
making put that into a slightly
different category like
the playing it out in a way that is
evocative or
enabling of growth together and we've
also spoken about
the importance um or we've sort of
spoken about the
the fragmentation and the breakdown of
religious structures
where previously there had been a
congregation um and
before then we've got these notions of
tribe and we've just moved on to
speaking about how it's uh
inappropriate to sort of conduit what
was this um
multi-nodal network that one was a part
of
through like one specific point like one
specific person too much of a pivot um
and i'm feeling like i'm feeling like
there's actually
a lot obviously to save here in religion
um and i can appreciate the point about
um words becoming unworkable
in some important sense
and something that was coming to me i
think
that might thematically bring a lot of
this together it's the idea that's
spoken about quite a bit which is which
is that
you know the church is not the building
it's the people who have the capacity to
build churches
um and concrete you know concrete
churches is actually really helpful to
get through the night to get to the next
day
it's just that we want to not mistake
the church
for the actual thing it's our capacity
to religion as
reconnect together to in an ongoing
sense
realize what
the kind of um wandering structure
enabling of our ongoing adaptivity
and um protection from that which would
sort of
pull us apart or too much entropy
um or what have you so that we can um go
out and face
another day that we can rejuvenate you
know
this idea of a kind of a integration as
um metabolizing in good company
was something that came to me the other
day that i quite liked and was something
i so realized i was seeking after some
particular sort of energetic expenditure
just to hang out with friends and eat
some food which is something difficult
for me at the moment
because we're under curfew here or in
fact we're not now as of a couple days
ago
but we were for like 10 weeks or so in
melbourne which has been quite a trip
um something else was this um
this frustration with religion as
too much of a concrete authority
but that if we can shift this to some
sort of more flexible
religion as ennobling and enabling of
our authorship
over our connectedness together on an
ongoing basis that this is kind of
helpful
um but i i wonder about you know it's
part of me that wants to actually
um being in digging a little bit to what
we mean by science
because i'm seeing science here is in
fact
not the container within which
everything else is sitting
and in fact that that the curious spirit
of the scientific approach to the world
to continually sort of disconfirm what
one previously thought to be the case
and continue to move towards
some sort of um more real pattern
in that sense is itself the will for
that
we can just as well say is more lit by
something you know
inflamed by something that we can refer
to in a more metaphysical sense which is
something that
at least in my sort of coherence making
of my own process is something that
plays a very sort of um important role
there
and it kind of partly comes up in this
notion of
psyche that we've presence just towards
the end here is that it will find a way
you know it will find a way in whatever
the context is to
make itself um to realize itself
um and so what i'm hearing um
and please like maybe this is not so
i like it i'm hoping this kind of
synthesizes in a helpful way
what i'm hearing is that
something of what we mean by science the
the
methodology of observation and um
you know better epistemics in that kind
of
sense can help us understand what are
the most
effective ways of creating
game-like structures enabling
of participating in the emerging context
of our time
so that we can in fact let what in us is
sort of transcendentally available
to reconnect with each other in this way
of
friendship fellowship and in some sense
are sort of this capacity we have to
extend
the hand with each other and in the face
of finitude
and the looming void we can be together
and transcend it and accept it
and enjoy ourselves along the way i'm
finding
science rather than being the
fundamental thing within
that can situate all of this is in fact
like in some sense
it's like of the essence of tool of the
essence of
technology that we must wield
appropriately but that
cannot in some sense we should not see
it as something that can
explain our nature which is why i think
this jungian
type approach just from this angle and a
metaphysical one as well can help i
think
provide a more rounded integris
notion of what it is to be fundamentally
in
as we're here how is this as a sort of
framing
yeah um i mean science at the end of the
day
the experimental method and whatever
it's it's one more psychotechnology
right
so one more tool in the kit um
it's a tool that does certain
particularly good things
as good at generating sort of certain
kinds of communal
questions it's very good at taking
small things and refining them to the
point of
being able to get a particular kind of
effect reliably right
and i think that that general thing i
mean you think about
you know we're having this call right
now um i think we're in three different
countries
aren't we i didn't ask where eric where
are you uh texas
texas so definitely we're in three
different countries yeah so
um so we're in three different countries
right
spanning across various points in the
globe we're bouncing the off
satellites it's going through fiber
optic cables right
all of this comes out of a technological
innovation which was you know a little
over 100 years ago
alexander graham bell speaks into a
piece of you know compressive carbon
and like three meters away in another
room
his butler whatever picks up the line
and he hears
watson come here that was only 100 years
ago our ability to technically refine
things once we
poke a hole right with science is
astounded we're
very good at that and so you know there
are certain kinds of questions that i
think science can't really get at i mean
this is jung's point essentially
speaking about
um i about sort of um
the relationship between the self and
god
and and how that fits together with
agnosticism right which is
you know at some level it's just
epistemologically impossible
to get confirmation or disconfirmation
of the existence of god
what experience or evidence could you
receive
that would actually definitively you
might become quite
you might develop conviction but like in
a philosophical epistemological sense
there's no way to prove or disprove the
existence
it doesn't matter what happens the sky
could crack open and beard man could
lean out and say i'm god
and the next day we'd all be arguing
about what happened
right even if we agreed on what we saw
we would be disagreeing on the
interpretation
and people would be like ah it's
probably some kind of seismic effect
jittering your temporal lobes or that
could have been a nearby alien
or who the hell knows right but young's
point is a good one
which is however it's sort of
indisputable when you look in the data
that
people have encounters with something
deep within their own psyche which
by its nature appears using the kind of
forms and language right the divine
grammar
that when we have these encounters with
the self
like what smashes in speaks in metaphor
riddle and and strange melded opposites
and paradox if that's how it hits us
is that ultimately an experience of god
impossible to tell
but the point is that if you don't have
a relationship with that
thing with that aspect in your
personality you're missing out on a
profound dimension of human experience
that's part of our shared inheritance
and
um and you know moreover if if you want
to have a relationship with it
you are in some ways backed into
speaking the language it chooses to
speak
which chakra is symbols and rituals and
right like that's how it speaks and
that's how it it's how you can interface
right
in the way that poetry cuts more than
prose
if you know what i mean like a poem has
a like a concentrated charge to it
and you know there's using religious
language and symbolism that way has that
kind of concentrated charge
so you end up doing the same thing
whether you're addressing just some like
you know genetic predisposition that you
have to have a little twist in your
brain that does
such and such and such or whether you
are in some sense dealing with
you know the the uh the boiling heart of
creation
uh doesn't matter you got to deal with
it kind of in the same way
so science i think can't answer
questions like that like there are
mysteries that in my opinion science
cannot
get at i sometimes wonder if
consciousness is one of those i mean i
do work in that area so i have high
hopes that
if we're making actual progress but if
i'm honest
like the hard problem is a hard problem
yeah and the problems of consciousness
are hard and there are lots of these
things you know that
science ultimately can't get at there's
a there's a horizon of mystery you know
um but what it's super good at
is these like concentrated hole poking
exercises
which then open a possibility and that's
what science does and once it's
right you can't disprove things right
but you can you can make the possibility
of something real like so you only need
whatever one black swan to prove the
existence of black swans
right you need one jab one credible
jab with science and then we can
elaborate the hell out of it
and if that jab is is is something that
lets us
poke through i think these like you know
these concrete barriers these
filmy things that we have between us
and some kind of more authentic
relationship with each other with nature
with
being right then if science can just
get the hole in there based on studying
what religion has already been doing
then everybody else in science can just
go at it and pull that thing open and in
100 years we've got
whatever the transition is to where we
are now technologically with
telecommunications equivalent is you
know
um that's that's where i place my hope
in science and it's fantastically good
at doing that particular thing
and i think some people are scared
sometimes i'm scared about
you know some the instrument the
instrumentalization
i guess of the sacred you know um
and i used to work in that field that's
a whole other story um
but um but i don't know i think there's
a lot of promise
there was something that jumped out
about what you had just said tim and how
it bounced off what eric said and
what i thought was it's interesting you
guys have talked about
this like the the issues that people
have and i realized it's like oh
it's the conflation of abstraction and
concreteness
in both directions when you're talking
about the concrete
boxes right and every time you say it i
find the song little boxes running
through my head you know that song yeah
yeah little box is made of ticky tacky
oh it's good
there's a death cab for cutie version
that i quite like i recommend
so uh you know little boxes right and
and these like nested boxes
and what is that that's us you know what
are the boxes the boxes are abstractions
but they're abstractions that we take to
be concrete right right
and then tim what you were mentioning is
is sort of the opposite right it's this
conflation where
we take things that are concrete and we
treat them
abstractly we treat them highly
abstractly and so we seem to get jammed
in both
directions right um
and i don't remember where that thought
was pointing but it did occur to me
yeah and the thing that arises in me is
that actually touches beautifully
on um what i see as like the marriage
that can happen between science and the
sacred
is deciding what can be cr
what can be concretized and what is
actually
made more sacred through concretizing it
which i think is the realm of science
and then what needs to not be
concretized
that needs to stay abstractions that
needs to stay symbolic and that that's
actually how you get the most
you know like the reason we concretize
is to attempt to get more functionality
or usefulness out of it and that by not
concretizing the sacred you actually
get the function that you seek from
concretizing it like one of the things
as a coach that comes up more
like especially for people who are just
beginning to use
plants to like alter consciousness is do
not concretize
the symbols and people want to
concretize the symbols that
make them feel huge and god-like and
grand
and then anything that comes that is
scary i'll leave that in
abstraction and it comes up in dream
interpretation all the time
and that feels like like
if we can discern between the usefulness
of what needs to be concretized and what
needs to be left symbolic i think that
that's how we can
get the most out of what feels like
these two dominant spheres which is like
the essence of science and the essence
of the sacred
mm-hmm
yeah the it's interesting it
for sure with dream interpretation right
um
there's always that and even i
had this in in analysis
there's always this tendency to hit the
like the facile
interpretation right the simplest thing
you know you dream about
your aunt and it's like oh it's about my
aunt it's like no it isn't
no it's about you
you know or it's it's not it's
transitive right right so it points both
ways and but that's even harder
to really wrap your head around the idea
that it's like yes it points into the
world
but also it's pointing to yourself and
the genius of the dream maker
is that it manages to perfectly clothe
one
to the other it's it's the the bone mo
right the fact where you know a really
good
word in a poem is not accidental and
it's just so
right and dreams are just so in that
young way it's like
that's a big difference in some ways
right between the union and the freudian
it's like 100 yes a pen and a knife
aren't
just penises i mean maybe they are a bit
but
you know if there's a knife in your
dream it's because it's a knife
it's a knife and not something else and
so what's a knife
why that it's not accidental why a knife
and so you know that but getting that
down that like
fine-tuning the level of abstraction and
getting it pointing in both directions
it's hard
yeah yeah it's hard um that can help us
with this and is there a myth that can
help sort of um
place this relationship between the
abstraction and the concrete as we've
come to use them in this conversation
because i don't i have them in some ways
i have them locked but
in another sense i find myself looking
for more clarity
for the one eric was talking about which
is this like
as people are doing this work they often
want to concretize the symbols that
inflate them
right they want to turn things into good
like talesmans they can clutch onto so
they can smash through the rest of their
life
uh icarus it's the myth of icarus that's
the classic inflation myth
you know so you trapped in the labyrinth
right
um because your father is the labyrinth
maker because
some king's wife slept with a sacred
bowl they always go way back right they
always chain into each other but the
point is you're stuck in a labyrinth
and your father of course is brilliant
uh
and and a god-like kind of creator and
so he fashions wings
but he warns you don't fly too high
don't fly too low
it's goldilocks don't fly too high don't
fly too low we always remember that too
high
we never remember the too low right we
never we always remember because that's
what he did right he flies up towards
the sun and in so doing
heats up too much and he's in the drink
but he equally could have if he had
flown too low
right he would have picked up too much
moisture on the wings
and so this this middle path right and
somehow being able to transition those
is sort of central
in some way icarus i mean think about
what to fly as a bird you've got
muscular action but you're also like
riding up drafts and
there's a dynamic quality to it to going
through the middle
and yeah for sure with with plant
teachers
with mystical experiences generally um
certainly with meditative experiences
the
the drive towards inflation is so
powerful and it's so tricky um it wants
to convince you that you are you know
the archetype yeah that you're the right
you're the new messiah
congrats right and it can be very
convincing the thing i always tell my
students is um
if you think you've reached
enlightenment spend the weekend with
your family
yep ramdas yup right
yes ramdas that's right yeah so um
you know cause like nothing lances that
faster than having your old horseshit
adolescent complexes rage all over the
about place myth of icarus is that the
other
like where people default so it feels
like when the psyche hits an obstacle in
life if it doesn't want to
actually contend with being transformed
by the obstacle the two things that
we'll tend to do is either inflate
or try to depress below it and icarus
feels like the perfect example like
a lot of people will destroy themselves
through false stories
so they don't even begin to contend with
transformation
and then other people will try to
inflate above it so they again do not
have to contend with transformation
and you know that brings us full circle
i think that that's actually
why the hero's journey when looked at as
an archetypical map to guide you to
transforming the ego and the presence of
what the self calls you to face
seems to be the most useful guide map as
you know a quote unquote coach that i
have found so far in my life
yeah i think i think you've really got
something there like
um you know the the idea is you're
trying to fly this middle ground and
it's like there are rules to some extent
i you know there aren't really but there
sort of are
and right and that in and of itself is
confusing as hell
and so people's responses are they dive
too low
and then they say there are rules and
these are the rules and i know
the rules right and they do not flex and
i'd rather be certain and wrong
than than to bother to
shake that off and you know that way
lies all kinds of things right i think
in some ways like you know dogmatic
dawkins style new atheism
is not much different than
fundamentalism in that sense right
uh it's just that it's like no no no no
and i know and that is its own form of
hubris
um and just like you know whatever
general absurdity uh so you know that's
to go low
and if you want to go high what do you
do you puff yourself up real far and say
well luckily rules don't apply to me
i transcend the rules through my very
being
and the thing is they're both they've
got something to them
yeah right but divorced from each other
you know it's a nightmare um you know
it's a
it's a nightmare so and then you end up
in the drink
no matter what you do it's not so bad to
go in the drink to be fair
that's that's the whole bottom half of
the hero's journey get in the drink
yeah yeah so i'm hearing a lot of the um
the ongoing need to learn how to make uh
boats we can sail in in this time
you know now maybe boats aren't getting
off the air there so it needs to be some
sort of hovercraft just to like stick
with the icarus thing
oh boats are going to come back yeah
yeah yeah well
sailboats are awesome
yeah yeah it seems um
yeah something i'm increasingly
fascinated by is the kind of
as i mentioned earlier the what you
might call the sort of
archetypes of what enables optimal
or at least good generativity in
conversation we might just say like what
makes for a good group of friends even
what makes that's actually adapting to
an environment
you know able to build and
essentially take care of what needs to
be taken care of
um as they all become
who they are you know this notion of the
self that calls that
you speak to eric um
i often sense that the
process of individuation in jung and i
haven't read
enough to be um to be sure of this
but um some sort of concern that i've
developed
um particularly as well
sort of analyzing or observing the
jordan peterson phenomenon
and how he addresses just just that
whole
that whole journey on ongoing journey
and what that ended up
crystallizing in terms of a message
in terms of individual responsibility
and um
self-authorship fundamentally which is
the fourth stage in
keegan's developmental model the fifth
being um
something beyond self-authoring i forget
the exact name he gives to it do you
do you recall that it's it's it anyway
it's it's like it's like a
trans-paradigmatic thing it's like an
inter it's like an interdependency the
recognition of interdependency
so beyond self-authorship how
can we become together um what we need
to be
so that there's this concept of the
lookout that i really like that a guy
called tyson yonko porter speaks about
in his book
sound talk but basically it's an in
indigenous concept
i used to something similar came to me
after a dmt experience once
to do with the importance of
appreciating the beauty around me but
also to push
just beyond it appropriately just to
advance the station
my station but only after i'd um really
come to appreciate exactly where i was
in some sense and so
the lookout is something like okay so
what of this domain of complexity this
domain
that i'm um custodian for
um what is mine to be in this kind of
caring reciprocal relationship with and
what is someone else's and how we all
working together to
together tend to the ecology which is
supporting us all and enabling us all to
sort of individuate in some sense the
one thing as an interdependent
prosecutor cycle of becoming or
a certain sort of transformation
and this notion of the self in the
jungian sense
often i think i think when people relate
to it certainly i did
when i was first encountering the ideas
um
i think i saw it as something perhaps a
little bit too isolated
interpreting it from the self-authorship
point of view where it was though
there was something for me to become
um in a way that maybe didn't
necessarily
take into account the the the need for
that to be part of let's say
a tribe and to be part of a contributing
element
to that which was the eternal creation
of the context
which actually has to be there in order
for me to be who i need to be anyway
um and so i'm wondering if if if it
makes sense to extend the notion of the
self or if you
already incorporates this into a sort of
understanding well i'm
but how i relate to this kind of um how
i relate to this sun in the solar system
of the self as this thing which
projects its light and sort of cools to
me it's both an ember and an echo in
some sense
that acorn like nature but also the echo
back of its projection of what it can
become
is that it's a kind of it's it's it's
it's a it's a moving center like the
fabric that
in each of us the ember is um
it's a it's a it's a collective flame in
that sense and we each are responsible
for our appropriate
portions of the fabric and we switch
sides and we have different roles and
all the rest of it
but we take responsibility for the
different sort of niches which together
constitute this interdependent ecology
and all of that in some sense itself
from the sense of the
from a sense of monism from a sense of
we're all connected man
this ongoing recreation
um and there's something inherently
transactive about that
i'm just wondering if if there can be a
critique made of young and i'm not the
one to make it because i can't speak to
what the man
truly finally really said there's
obviously lots of different
interpretations
but is there a critique to be made of
jung that in some sense
the individual's relationship to the
collective unconscious even
was altogether perhaps a little bit too
individual and
not enough of a truly involved
participatory remaking of that very
fabric of the collective unconscious if
you can
kind of see what i'm trying to gesture
yeah i mean so it's almost tricky
right because young is writing over half
a century
and his ideas are changing and
you know when you're sort of trying to
teach this material it's always tricky
because people like well he says this
here but he says this here
and it's like yep it's true that's those
are two different things that he said 25
years apart
so you should get to work on reconciling
those things
um you know
one of the yeah i mean no i think i
think you're right in some ways right
jung is speaking to some extent and it's
an earlier version of it but out of the
framework of like
you know western individualism
and that kind of like atomized vision of
the individual i mean you know
individuation even typically as a term
more often than not triggers people
sense that they're going to become
you know an individual right like a
radical monad
you know highly unified and you know
it's only it's only when
you kind of get into the concept that
you're pointing out that it's like it's
not that simple
you're in fact you're becoming highly
individual you are shedding yourself of
your idea that you are
unitive um and and then
you are undergoing something that yes
involves integration but not just
integration it involves integration
and dissociation repeatedly between
different parts
to form a far more complex and dynamic
inner community right i think takes it
for granted
in some sense that there is an outer
community because
you know from 1910 through to 1960
those things were still if not perfectly
intact more in intact than they are now
right there were still bowling leagues
and church picnics
and like right thing the sorts of things
that people used to
to have community structures at large
now at the same time
you know one of the things the self
pretty notoriously calls people to do is
separate themselves from the tribe right
and to to to walk into the desert to go
into the cave
to put oneself into the monastery like
sometimes separating oneself out but
it's the same thing it's integration
dissociation and you know
one of the most powerful experiences i i
had
in my life for sure um as an experience
of the self was
um during my kind of uh second and and
quite powerful
uh iboga experience and
i had primed myself for the idea of i
was doing some some kabbalistic work so
it won't get too deep but
i was combining a boga with kabbalah and
i was planning to ascend to
teferet the solar sphere okay and the
idea was i would
encounter the resurrecting gods right
these are your gods that come back to
life you'd think being raised christian
that the god i might encounter would be
you know jesus or maybe a mithra
or something you know uh but when i
actually
sort of got to this space this radiant
golden
space and the psyche as it were um i
encountered superman
this surprised me tremendously i love it
um i mean it makes much more sense
that would have had a far more basic
impact on me and i could go on about
that
but the point is i encountered superman
who had this dialogue with superman
and one of the things that came out of
that as things that have come out with
some of these other experiences that
were in some cases
based in altered states that were sort
of exogenous
in some way and in some cases fully
endogenous right these
these things that broke through the
bottom of the bucket um
was that very often what these things
did when i connected with this was that
yes sometimes it would sort of drive me
into the wilderness
but a lot of the time and certainly with
this one with superman and with some of
those experiences it was like
okay now it's time to go back to
civilization like it's time to rejoin
the tribe
so and i think that's something that
iboga
and ayahuasca both my experience with a
boga more so than ayahuasca
ayahuasca when i asked it about my human
relationships was like
no that doesn't matter here are 19 neon
jaguar gods um that was my experience
but boga was very concerned with ground
level
human ties right right and to whatever
extent and i think
you know it's reasonable to think of
those things as legitimate
um sort of mystical experiences and
connections i think that they have this
way
of pulling people back to community
when that's what's needed and that it
in some sense mirrors and reflects and
that's the union idea your inner
community and your outer community
right exactly it's all transactive right
um that's why we project onto people and
so you know um so i'm gonna have to go
after this but
but the thing that comes up in response
to your question
is that um so my understanding is that
one of jung's favorite stories at the
end of his life was the
rainmaker story and i think the
rainmaker story perfectly answers this
question
and so in brief the story is his friend
is in china
is at a village and the village is going
through a drought and
the westerner you know who sees the
world through the western lens
is wondering like what the town's people
or what the village people are going to
do about this drought
and the people tell them don't worry
we're waiting on the rainmaker
and this westerner is like you know what
the hell is a rainmaker
and this old man eventually comes to the
village and the town or the village
people go to him and they take him to
a hut at the edge of the village and
they put him in the hut and the
westerner watches is that he stays in
this hut for three days
and then at the end of the third day it
starts raining and the rainmaker emerges
out of the hut and the westerner goes up
to him and he asks him what did you do
how did you do this and the rainmaker
said
i come from a place where the land is in
order and because the land
is in order the land does what it must
do when i came to this place the land
was out of order and i got infected
so i had to go put myself in order and
once i put myself in order the land
came into order and the land did what it
had to do and my understanding of that
this
in this embodies what the individuation
process is
and it's that you have to get away
in order to come into order with
yourself
and then the natural byproduct of being
in order in yourself is you bring that
order to the environment and improve the
environment
and that it will always bring you back
to the community
perfect
[Music]
thank you for listening and if you enjoy
these podcasts please consider sharing
them or leaving a review
and perhaps also to consider supporting
it on patreon.com
voicecraft your support makes a
life-changing difference and a
life-affirming impact
it will help sustain the podcast build
the network and make possible more
community events and educational
resources
read about member benefits at
patreon.com
voicecraft there are breadcrumbs to
follow if you look